Guide to the Henry Geldzahler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- December 1999 Acquisition, circa 1945-1996; 1; 39.04; (43 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1986, undated (Box 9, Folder 351)
    1) Basquiat postcard to Geldzahler from Mark Gero, October 26, 1986, ink; 2) Venice postcard to Geldzahler from Robert Irwin - ink, no date; 3) 1 page legal paper handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from Robert Irwin - February 17, 1965. Recto and verso, concerning his new paintings; 4) 4 page handwritten letter (pencil) to Geldzahler from Jasper Johns - no date. Concerning his stay in Japan, and progress on new paintings, "Souvenir" and "Watchman." Signed "Japage "; 5) 5 page handwritten letter (pencil) to Geldzahler from Jasper Johns - no date. Regarding Japanese customs, and the progress of his work; 6) 1 page notebook paper, handwritten letter (ink) to Geldzahler from Paul Johnson - no date; 7) 1 page xerox of typed letter to Ray Johnson from Avedon Studio - in envelope; 8) 2 page typed xerox letter to Geldzahler with hand drawings from Ray Johnson - April 23, 1985 - in envelope; 9) 2 page xerox of artwork - 1 page handwritten note (pencil) to Geldzahler from Ray Johnson, June 2, 1986 - in envelope; 10) 2 page letter (typed and pencil) to Geldzahler from Ray Johnson, June 11, 1986 - in envelope; 11) 4 page typed, hand signed (ink) letter to Geldzahler from Dan Judson, November 12, 1985 - in envelope; 12) 1 page handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from Scott Kilgaur - no date; 13) 5, 1 page typed hand signed letters from Ed Koch to Geldzahler; 2 xerox copies of October 26th, 1982 letter; 14) 2 page handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from Kusama - no date; 15) 1 page handwritten (ink) note from Scott Kilgour - no date; 16) 1 page handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from Scott Kilgour - March 14 - no year; 17) Herzl year postcard to Geldzahler from Kitaj - no date - ink; 18) ½ page (ripped notebook paper) handwritten (ink) note to Geldzahler and RF from Kitaj - no date.
  - Correspondence and Writings: 1 page typed letter to Geldzahler from Charles Michener at Bantam Books, returning; approximately 30 page outline for Modern Art in America - in a folder; loose bound xerox manuscript Selected Writings 1984-1984 by Geldzahler; loose bound xerox manuscript Selected Writings 1984-1985 by Geldzahler; loose bound xerox manuscript Writings 1987 by Geldzahler. approximately 300 pages (Box 9, Folder 352)
  - Correspondence and Writings: National Endowment for the Arts and New York City Department of Cultural Affairs (Box 9, Folder 353)
    1) The New Yorker, December 8, 1980 - handwritten note (ink) on cover by Geldzahler "George Steiner on Anthony Blunt"; 2) Paste board photo book by Henry Strait Settlement to Geldzahler regarding Visit - photos of Geldzahler with children; 3) 3 page typed, hand corr. (pencil) essay "A Collector's Apartment" by Geldzahler in folder; 4) Approximately 100 pages in folder - all xeroxes of transcripts from City Council Hearings, containing: 11 pages, 1984 testimony before Congressional Committee overseeing NEA, 3 xeroxes of same; 3 pages typed "Talking Points" to Frank Hodsell, Chairman NEA circa 1984. A second copy, heavily edited by Geldzahler in pencil; 5 page transcript of Geldzahler talk on the NEA, undated.; 1 page as above; 4 pages testimony of Geldzahler before Congressional House Panel on NEA 5/21/82. A second copy with Geldzahler edits in pen; 1 page handwritten notes by Geldzahler on funding for the arts; 2 page letter to Geldzahler from Rep. Paul Simon on Federal funding for the arts; 5) File containing: Various typescripts of speeches by Geldzahler for ceremonies during his years as NYC Commissioner of Cultural Affairs: Studio Museum of Harlem dedication with Geldzahler annotations; NY Hall of Science address; St John the Divine Cathedral renovations, with Geldzahler annotated; 3/11/82 City Council hearings, 7 page transcript: a complete overview of how the Department of Cultural Affairs functions as an agency; 1 pg, "Arts Exposure" plan; 2 page 6/30/82 "Celebrate Brooklyn" festival; 1 page 5/27/82 El Museo del barrio; 1 page 2/8/82 Speech honoring Martin Segal of Gulf and Western Company; 2 pages 6/7/82 Contemp Art at One Penn Plaza; 1 page 6/29/82 Rotterdam Poetry Festival
  - 6 various catalogues and announcements from Watari Gallery, Japan (Box 9, Folder 354)
  - Hockney: approximately 100 page file of mostly correspondence from or about Hockney - including 30 handwritten, ink, letters to Geldzahler from Hockney; 25 handwritten postcards - also Metropolitan Museum slide list, 1970-1981 (Box 9, Folder 355)
  - Warhol - Composite Article: approximately 80 page file - 4 xerox sets of article on Warhol by Geldzahler, 1964-1989. Includes original typescript with emendations in hand by Geldzahler on: Warhol's boxes (1 page, circa 1964) and an untitled 2 page essay on AW's films. Compiled for Art Interaction 1964 (Box 9, Folder 356)
  - Andy Warhol Movies "Six Encounters": 14 pages handwritten notes (ink and red felt pen) (Box 9, Folder 357)
  - Dan Dailey: Glass Artist: approximately 125 page file - mostly xeroxes of sketches but also, 1 page handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler (12/2/86); 3 pages handwritten notes by Geldzahler on legal paper and 4 page typed original essay, hand corrected (ink) by Geldzahler for D.D. catalogue and various drafts of same; 1 page typed letter to Geldzahler from D.D. handsigned (ink) 11/20/86; various clippings and articles - some with handwritten notes by Geldzahler in margins., 1986 (Box 9, Folder 358)
  - Chihuly: 3 page xerox draft, hand corrected (ink) "Chihuly at the Louvre: Objets de Verre." (Box 9, Folder 359)
  - DV8: 1 copy magazine (preview issue) with press release, advertising rates, etc. (Box 9, Folder 360)
  - L.I.U.: correspondence, schedule and exhibition invitation cards for August-September show 1987, ad copy Island University - Geldzahler to speak at (4 page file) (Box 9, Folder 361)
  - Dia Foundation: 1 page typed letter to Geldzahler regarding funding for catalogues; 1 page handwritten notes (ink) by Geldzahler on legal paper (alarm codes) (Box 9, Folder 362)
  - Calif; Magazine March 1984: 9 page xeroxes of California artists (Box 9, Folder 363)
  - Kenneth Nolan Paper Works: 11 page typed chronology and selected exhibition list; catalogue - Duke University, March-April 1983 and clippings; catalogue for artist Rufino-Tamayo-Albatina, March-April 1983; various xerox clippings on Tamayo (Box 9, Folder 364)
  - N.Y.P.L.: 2 page file - 2 typed letters to Geldzahler on library business (Box 9, Folder 365)
  - Video Tape File: 13 pages xerox list for various commercial videos (Box 9, Folder 366)
  - Noguchi Lamps: 1 catalogue from Noguchi Foundation - all Akari lamps, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 367)
  - Pop Art Australia Show: 6 page xerox of review in Art Network - "Pop Art 1955-1970" by Julie Ewington (Box 9, Folder 368)
  - Jagger House: Bills Appraisals: 5 page file regarding Southampton property (Box 9, Folder 369)
  - Hockney: 18 page xerox draft of essay by Geldzahler "David Hockney, Young and Older" (Box 10, Folder 370)
  - Bibliographies: approximately 70 page file - typed and handwritten bibliographies for artists: Roy Lichtenstein, Adolf Gottlieb, Philip Guston, Hans Hofmann, Josef Albers, Alexander Calder, Milton Avery, Joseph Cornell, Stuart Davis, Burgoyne Diller, Dan Flavin, Helen Frankenthaler, Arshile Gorley (Box 10, Folder 371)
  - Modern Art in America: approximately 35 page file - 4 page original typed "Outline to Finish MA in A" and 4 xerox copies; stapled proposal. 1) Preface; 2) Outline; 3) About the book; 4) About the author - xerox (Box 10, Folder 372)
  - Legal Documents: approximately 25 page file - mostly regarding disappearance of rug from storage and lawsuit (Box 10, Folder 373)
  - Current Projects: approximately 25 page file - all business correspondence - mostly requests for appearances, articles written, or art loans (Box 10, Folder 374)
  - Currently On Hold: approximately 10 page file - all business correspondence, mostly requests for Geldzahler's services (Box 10, Folder 375)
  - Hoffman #1: approximately 60 page file and catalogues all xeroxes of articles on Hans Hoffman, plus artist bibliography and slide lists; catalogues from - Worth Ryder Art Gallery, University of California, April 2-May 3, 1964; Stanford Art Museum, June 22-August 17, 1966; André Emmerich Gallery, January 8-January 27, 1972, 1964-1972, undated (Box 10, Folder 376)
  - Hofmann #2 - 1: approximately 30 pages typed, original notes and drafts for Hans Hofmann - hand corrected, cut and pasted; 15 page typed xerox final draft "Hans Hofmann"; approximately 20 page xeroxes from books on Hofmann; Hans Hofmann: The Renate Series, Metropolitan Museum, intro. by Geldzahler; Hofmann by Clement Greenberg, published 1961 editions Georges Fall, Paris - inscribed to Geldzahler by Hans Hofmann, ink; Bennington College Alumnae Quarterly, Vol. VII, no. 1, page 21 and 22 on Hofmann (Box 10, Folder 377)
  - Cultural Affairs: 2 copies of Cultural Affairs Department Report: July 1979-December 1980; 1 page typed, original, hand corrected (ink) draft of Geldzahler's resignation letter to Ed Koch; 2 postcards from school children, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 378)
  - Miscellaneous: approximately 15 page cut up xeroxes of "Determining Aesthetic Values" (Box 10, Folder 379)
  - Sao Paulo Bienal: approximately 150 page file, mostly business correspondence regarding Geldzahler's participation as curator (fees, travel plans, etc.) for Chihuly and Hockney rooms - included are statements by Geldzahler on Chihuly and Hockney for catalogue (Box 10, Folder 380)
    1) In envelope: approximately 50 page typed, hand corrected drafts on Chihuly and correspondence regarding article; 2) Artes magazine (undated) page 38 on Bienal; 3) in envelope - xeroxes of fax regarding meeting with Carlos von Schmidt, Geldzahler and Karen Chambers and 9 color Polaroids of Hockney's work.
  - Henry Geldzahler. Press comments, clippings and reviews (Box 10, Folder 380A)
  - Tom Slaughter: 5 xerox copies of two page typed "Introducing Tom Slaughter" by Geldzahler; 6 color snapshots of artwork; 2 typed 1 page hand signed (ink) letters to Geldzahler (April 9, June 13, 1988); 1 8x10 color photo proof sheet; 1 postcard of hat signed by T.S., 1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 381)
  - Norman Stone: Wilmarth Sale: 5 color slides; 9 color transparencies of Chihuly; 2 typed 1 page hand signed letters to Geldzahler from Norman Stone, 1 xerox (1 page) of letter to Stone from Geldzahler regarding Wilmarth sculptures and prices (Box 10, Folder 382)
  - Howard Stein: 1 page typed, original hand corrected letter, unsigned from Geldzahler to Howard Stein (Box 10, Folder 383)
  - Warhol Interview Magazine: 13 page typed, original essay: "Henry Geldzahler: Andy Warhol Interview Magazine." A history of the magazine by Geldzahler for a Japanese publication (Box 10, Folder 384)
  - Warhol Museum of Modern Art: approximately 30 page file - correspondence requesting statement from Geldzahler on Warhol and 11 pages of various typed, hand corrected drafts of Geldzahler's statement for 1989 retrospected at Museum of Modern Art (Box 10, Folder 385)
  - 100 Warhols: 7 pages from Connoisseur magazine "The Warhol Collection"; 22 pages of various typed drafts of articles by Geldzahler: "Andy Warhol for British Vogue: The Recording Angel," "One Hundred Andy Warhols" and "Warhol of Sotheby's." (Box 10, Folder 386)
  - Chris Wilmarth: approximately 50 page file - mostly xeroxes of art-work - three 1 page handwritten letters to Geldzahler from C.W. (ink - March 20, '87 includes 3 sketches of sculptures; April 28, 1985; 6 September 1983); 2 page typed original, hand corrected statement by Geldzahler for C.W. memorial services; business correspondence regarding Wilmarth artwork (Box 10, Folder 387)
  - Roy Lichtenstein: approximately 100 page file - mostly drafts (original and xerox, typed, hand corrected, cut and pasted; plus handwritten notes) for "Lichtenstein: The Picasso Women 1962-64"; some xeroxes of R.L's Picassos, 2 color transparencies (Box 10, Folder 388)
    1) 15 pages of xeroxed drafts with emendations in Geldzahler's hand; 2) 15 pages of handwritten notes on Roy L., on legal paper and notebook paper, and 5 pages of 5 x 7" legal pad notes; 3) 20 pages original typescript heavily edited, cut and pasted by Geldzahler. Drafts of essay "Lichtenstein's Picassos" and "Mirror Ptgs" essays; 4) envelope with cover letter from designer A. McCall, containing final orig typescript (8 pages) of the essay, a xerox of same with edits in pencil, and a clean xeroxed draft of essay with edits incorporated (10 pages).
  - American Museum of Moving Image: approximately 20 page file regarding information on museum; 1 page xerox of letter to Avery Fischer from Geldzahler regarding Museum and correspondence from museum to Geldzahler (Box 10, Folder 389)
  - Israel: approximately 30 page file - mostly business correspondence regarding symposium of Tel Aviv manuscripteum; 5 page handwritten notes by Geldzahler - ink on legal paper, an account of his visits to Israel, and its museums (Box 10, Folder 390)
  - Dale Chihuly: approximately 80 page file - mostly drafts of essay by Robert Hobbs with emendations by Geldzahler; 2 page typed essay by Geldzahler "The Stubborn Voice from Within" on William Morris' glasswork; one 2 page handwritten, ink, (6/14/88) letter to Geldzahler from D.C.; 1 page typed, hand signed (pencil) 10/6/86 letter from D.C. to Geldzahler; 4 color transparencies and 1 color Polaroid. 6 pages orig typescript with edits by Geldzahler and RF "Class Glass," on Chihuly, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 391)
  - Dale Chihuly: catalogue Elements: Five Installations - Whitney Museum, December-January 1988 - on the cover is a letter to Geldzahler from D.C. (ink); 3 page slides; 9 pages ripped out of book of D.C. work; handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from DC on back of Deborah Brown announcement, (August 20 1986); 1 page typed (December 29, 1986) letter to Geldzahler from D.C.; 3 page xerox, hand corrected "Chihuly at the Louvre" by Geldzahler (Box 10, Folder 392)
  - Karen Chambers--Chihuly secretary: approximately 20 page file, most business correspondence and 2 page xerox "Karen Chambers - The New Glass" by Geldzahler; 1 page typed (December 25, 1987) letter to Geldzahler from K.C., hand signed (ink) (Box 10, Folder 393)
  - Calliope Films: 6 page file - correspondence from Calliope to Geldzahler regarding Warhol film (Box 10, Folder 394)
  - Louise Bourgeois: 9 8x10 B&W photos of sculpture installation at DIA Bridgehampton, installed by Geldzahler; 9 xeroxes of artwork, inventory list and 2 page essay "The Tribe of One" and copies. All materials relating to Geldzahler's exhibition of LB at DIA Bridgehampton. Xerox of a letter by Louise B. making 2 changes in text (Box 10, Folder 395)
  - Bantam Books: 18 page proposal for Modern Art in America; letter from Bantam to Geldzahler regarding book (Box 10, Folder 396)
  - Henry G. Resume: approximately 30 page file - xerox of prepared resume and photos. A strip of four original 35mm negatives of Geldzahler by Hockney, and 1 copy negative of same portrait, for passport use (Box 10, Folder 397)
  - Writings by Geldzahler: approximately 300 page file - all xeroxes of essays, etc. by Geldzahler, mostly 1960's - inventory in front of file (Box 10, Folder 398)
  - Arman: approximately 60 page file - 3 pages typed hand corrected drafts of article by Geldzahler; 8 page essay by Geldzahler with extensive editing in RF's hand; 1 color transparency; ripped out pages from some magazine on Arman's work; correspondence between RF and Marisa Del Rey; 4 page typescript letter signed by Arman giving an extensive account of his work in metal sculpture since 1962, and of the series "Gods and Goddesses." (Box 11, Folder 399)
  - GLP Taxes 1976: approximately 10 page file - bank statements, rent schedules for G.L.P. Partners (Box 11, Folder 400)
  - Bills Outstanding: small file of bills, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 401)
  - Wilmarth - 2 8x10 B&W photos of sculptures; 1 color transparency (Box 11, Folder 402)
  - Business Men's Luncheon, Detroit: 9 page handwritten (ink) notes for talk, 1965 May 13 (Box 11, Folder 403)
  - NYC Dept of Cultural Affairs: approximately 200 page file - all business documents: annual reports, various memos, proposals, financial disclosure information, etc. giving an overview of the DCA circa 1978-1979 under Geldzahler. A listing of all 1967-1969 recipients of NEA visual arts fellowships (Box 11, Folder 404)
  - Chihuly: 20 color transparencies; 23 page xerox typed interview (Robert Kehlmann and Dale Chihuly) 3/5/89; slide list, 1989, undated (Box 11, Folder 405)
  - Notes: 5x8 bound notebook - first five pages written in by Geldzahler 1985 (ink); ten stray pages of notes, handwritten by Geldzahler stuck in, reflections on aesthetics (Box 11, Folder 406)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings (stories, photos, profiles) from newspapers and mags, relating to Geldzahler, 1969-1979 (Box 11, Folder 407)
  - Robson: 10 page typed short story (?) by Mona Robson - in envelope (Box 11, Folder 408)
  - Programs from events where Geldzahler spoke (Box 11, Folder 409)
  - Op-Ed Piece: approximately 20 page file - all drafts for NY Times Op Ed page - typed and handwritten notes (some on index cards) pen and pencil. Alternately titled, "The City as Patron" and "The Culture of New York." (Box 11, Folder 410)
  - Bio: approximately 15 page file - prepared biographical material on Geldzahler, plus two press photos (Box 11, Folder 411)
  - Selected Writings 1983-84: approximately 150 page file - the original printed essays - inventory in front of file, 1983-1984 (Box 11, Folder 412)
  - Ellsworth Kelly: 8 pages typed poems by EK (not for publication); 1 page letter to Geldzahler (August 23, 1986) handwritten (ink) from E.K., 1986, undated (Box 11, Folder 413)
  - Ellsworth Kelly: 21 page handwritten, ink, on legal paper for Kansas City museum lecture, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 414)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, containing several excellent and important unpublished early texts by Geldzahler. 22 page typescript "Origins and Early Developments of Abstract Art", Museum of Modern Art lecture 1963. Corrections in Geldzahler's hand; 25 page typed "Sao Paolo Bienal" xerox, hand corrected; 29 page typed carbon transcript of Museum of Modern Art talk 4/27/76; 26 page typed xerox "Approaching Clemente" and xerox copy of article in same Italian mag, 1963-1976, undated (Box 11, Folder 415)
  - Warhol (Box 11, Folder 416)
    1) 6 page color xeroxes of Warhol prints 1970-1980s; 2) Print lists (working material for Geldzahler's intro to Ronald Feldman's Warhol print raisonné; 3) 41 page typed Museum of Modern Art exhibition information including an extensive chronology of AW's life, extensively edited by Geldzahler; 4) 7 page typed xerox "Andy Warhol Today", draft by Geldzahler with extensive editing in his hand; 5) 6 page handwritten (ink) notes on legal paper, for Warhol print raisonné essay; 6) Memorial Mass card; 7) In envelope - Andy Warhol Myths postcard booklet; 8) Endangered Species postcard booklet; 9) Ten Portraits of Jews of the 20th Century - card collection for Lowe Art Museum show, September 6-28, 1980; 10) 10 pages typed strays - hand corr. from various Geldzahler writings on Warhol, xeroxed.
  - On Geldzahler: 2 copies: Japanese mag, Brutus 50 1982 (Box 11, Folder 417)
  - On Geldzahler: approximately 200 page file various articles on Geldzahler from the 1980's Hamptons Mag, Express The Economist plus clippings from newspapers (Box 11, Folder 418)
  - On Geldzahler: 1 copy - Art News, Oct 1982: "The Education of Geldzahler," a profile of Geldzahler as Commissioner, 1982 October (Box 11, Folder 419)
  - Architectural Digest: approximately 150 page file - contracts and correspondence regarding articles and numerous copies from mag of "California Dream Realized." (Box 11, Folder 420)
  - Geldzahler's Home: copies from mag featuring Geldzahler's townhouse on West 9th Street, NYC, Domus, August 1983 - Italian mag and other, unknown, possibly Architecture Digest. 5 page typescript draft with extensive editing in Geldzahler's hand on "The Collector's Aesthetic.", 1983, undated (Box 11, Folder 421)
  - Geldzahler on Warhol: approximately 20 page file - drafts, typed, hand corrected on Warhol for British Vogue; copy of Vogue article (Box 11, Folder 422)
  - Weatherspoon: approximately 15 page file - correspondence regarding loan of artworks by Geldzahler to the University of North Carolina, Greensboro gallery (Box 11, Folder 423)
  - Inventory of Artworks: Judson Warehouse: approximately 20 page file - inventory lists and agreements for storage of artwork (Box 11, Folder 424)
  - Weinberg: 6 page file - typed drafts of letters by Geldzahler recommending Jonathan Weinberg to a teaching position. (Box 11, Folder 425)
  - Jack Whitten: 2 page slides; 15 page xerox typed hand corrected essay on J.W.; 12 page J.W. chronology and bio material with Geldzahler's editing; Various correspondence from Studio Museum in Harlem; in envelope - 1 page handwritten (ink) letter to Geldzahler from J.W. 2/4/87; 33 page typed transcript of Geldzahler and JW interview; 5 pages typescript Intro on JW by Geldzahler with edits in his hand (Box 11, Folder 426)
  - Neil Williams: 1 page typed, hand corrected statement by Geldzahler on N.W., 7 page xeroxed typescript (Box 11, Folder 427)
  - Wylie: approximately 300 page file, including agreements, business correspondence plus numerous notes (typed, handwritten, xerox and original) regarding Modern Art in America and proposals (Box 11, Folder 428)
    Including: 1) 8 page orig typescript with edits in Geldzahler's hand: "James Rorimer and the Met," an account of Geldzahler's early days at the Met; 2) 5 page typed 1964 memo (retyped in 1980s) from Geldzahler to James Rorimer on the direction the MET Museum needs to take with 20th century art; 3) 11 pages, handwritten notes on Geldzahler's proposed volume "Modern Art in America."
  - Catalogues and Miscellaneous: Avedisian and Hennessy, Grey Art Gallery, February-March 1977; Christopher Wilmarth, Grey Art Gallery, January-February 1978; Ad Reinhardt, Betty Parsons Gallery, 1960; Programs for "Festival of the Arts '68", University of Kansas - Geldzahler on page 6; Who's Who certificate to Geldzahler, 1976-1977; New York, October 13, 1969 - 6 page article on "Henry's Show"; Poster for Larry Rivers exhibitions October 1977, Robert Miller Gallery, 1960-1978 (Box 11, Folder 429)
  - Dan Dailey: 2 page slides and 2 page xerox slide list; 1 page typed letter to Geldzahler 11/5/85, hand signed (ink), 1985, undated (Box 11, Folder 430)
  - Christo: 5 8x10 color photos, "Surrounded Islands", 1983 (Box 11, Folder 431)
  - Emilio Cruz: 1 page typed letter to Geldzahler (no date) hand signed (felt pen); 15 page typed poems (Box 11, Folder 432)
  - Unsorted materials (Box 12, Folder 8.1)